The Bhaktivedanta Book Trust International
Founder-Acharya: His Divine Grace A.C. Bhaktivedanta Swami Prabhupada

Rights and Permissions    Box 34074, Los Angeles, CA 90034 USA                               
Phone:  1-800-927-4152 (toll free in the USA)
Outside the US: +1 310 837-5283  ·  Fax: +1 310 837-1056
Send us e-mail


Permission for using BBT works



We strongly believe in “fair use.” So if all you want to do is make fair-use quotations, please feel free. We love to be quoted. 

Are you a student or teacher? Want to make incidental use of a BBT work in the course of your studies or teaching? An image, perhaps. Or a page or so of text. By all means, just feel free. 

Again if you’re a student or teacher and you want to publish an occasional BBT image on your website in an academic context, be our guest. Just please add our copyright notice: 

        Artwork courtesy of The
        Bhaktivedanta Book Trust
        International, Inc.
        www.krishna.com

And in your notice, please make www.krishna.com a link.

 
 For other uses, we ask you to first get our permission.

· Want to use BBT images outside an academic context?

· Or in a book or periodical? 

· Want to publish passages that go beyond fair use? 

· Or use BBT sounds, images, or text for something you’re going to sell? 

Please get in touch with us. 

Very often, all we’ll ask is a simple copyright notice. If you’re selling something, we may ask a very reasonable fee. 

Our contact info is at the top of this page. Or you can fill in our online request for permission.


T H A N K   Y O U


© 2005  The Bhaktivedanta Book Trust International. All rights reserved.

