VSOP87 Theory Equations Summary

Font: http://neoprogrammics.com/vsop87/
VSOP87 Theory Equations Summary Part 1

Font: http://neoprogrammics.com/vsop87/VSOP87_Equations_Summary_Part_1.html
Rectangular Coordinates (X,Y,Z)

All the VSOP87 series do essentially the same thing. They compute the co-ordinates of the planets for a given moment. The main difference is the type of co-ordinates in which the planetary positions are expressed. Depending on the application, one type of co-ordinate system may be more or less suitable or convenient than another for a particular purpose, so several VSOP87 series have been developed for this reason.

For computing the apparent geocentric planetary positions, like those we generally see tabulated in the standard astronomical almanacs for the ecliptic and equinox of the date, series C or D is generally the most convenient starting point for this purpose. VSOP87 series C is used to compute the heliocentric rectangular XYZ-co-ordinates or series D is used to compute the corresponding equivalent heliocentric spherical LBR-co-ordinates (see Part 2). They are different types of co-ordinates for expressing the same position in space.

In The Following VSOP87 Equations, We Will Apply The Following Variables

JDTT = Julian Day number corresponding to a given date and time (TT)
t = Julian millennia, corresponding to JDTT and reckoned from J2000.0

When we want to compute the position of a planet for a given date and time, we first compute the JDTT value corresponding to the TT and then compute the corresponding (t) value from it. This will be the actual value used as the time variable in the equations below.

t = JDTT − 2451545365250

The A,B,C values in each series term in the equations are taken from the original FORTRAN program data tables. There may be thousands of terms in a sub-series, each with its own table of unique A,B,C values. These values are used by the code generator tool to formulate the hard-coded numerical terms in the output source code.

A = Amplitude
B = Phase (not to be confused with the spherical B-co-ordinate)
C = Frequency

Indices used in the summation equations:
n = Sub-series order from 0 to 5
j = Index of term within sub-series (from 1 to k)
k = Total number of terms in sub-series (can be from 1 to multiple thousands)

There are two different types of VSOP87 co-ordinates - rectangular and spherical co-ordinates. These are the co-ordinates computed by the VSOP87 sub-series function modules generated by the Multi-Language VSOP87 Source Code Generator Tool.

X, Y, Z = Heliocentric Rectangular Coordinates in AU

R = Heliocentric radius vector (distance) in AU

1 AU (Astronomical Unit) = 149597870.691 km ±0.030 (NASA/JPL) = 92955807.267 mi

Speed of Light = 299792.458 km/s (NIST) = 186282.397 mi/s

Computing the Planetary Rectangular XYZ-Coordinates in AUs

VSOP87 Series A = Heliocentric ecliptical rectangular XYZ-coordinates - Equinox J2000.0
VSOP87 Series C = Heliocentric ecliptical rectangular XYZ-coordinates - Equinox of Date
VSOP87 Series E = Barycentric rectangular XYZ-coordinates - Equinox J2000.0

The VSOP87 A and C series correspond to the B and D series. The only difference is the type of co-ordinates used.

In the following summations, the A,B,C values we apply depends on the series we are using and were taken from the original FORTRAN data files for the corresponding sub-series.

There are six orders of XYZ sub-series summations (n=0 to n=5). The above sub-series summations are computed separately for each order (n=0 to n=5) for each of the k terms of the given sub-series. The essential source code to compute the numerical values of these co-ordinates for any given moment over spans of thousands of years can be generated by the VSOP87 Source Code Generator tool.

The six separate sub-series summations returned by the functions for the respective sub-series are then summed to obtain the final, complete rectangular XYZ-co-ordinates of the planet at the given time.

X=∑i=05xi=x0+x1+x2+x3+x4+x5

Y=∑i=05yi=y0+y1+y2+y3+y4+y5

Z=∑i=05zi=z0+z1+z2+z3+z4+z5

For each term of order (n), from 0 to 5, the VSOP87 (xn yn zn) sub-series summations
may be expressed as:

xn=⎛⎝∑j=1k AX,n,j⋅cos(BX,n,j + t⋅CX,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn

yn=⎛⎝∑j=1k AY,n,j⋅cos(BY,n,j + t⋅CY,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn

zn=⎛⎝∑j=1k AZ,n,j⋅cos(BZ,n,j + t⋅CZ,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn

Based on the above definitions, the complete VSOP87 solutions in terms of rectangular XYZ-coordinates may be expressed by the following set of general equations.

t=JDTT−2451545365250

X=∑n=05⎛⎝⎛⎝∑j=1k AX,n,j⋅cos(BX,n,j + t⋅CX,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn⎞⎠

Y=∑n=05⎛⎝⎛⎝∑j=1k AY,n,j⋅cos(BY,n,j + t⋅CY,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn⎞⎠

Z=∑n=05⎛⎝⎛⎝∑j=1k AZ,n,j⋅cos(BZ,n,j + t⋅CZ,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn⎞⎠

R = X2+Y2+Z2−−−−−−−−−−−−√

As an example, for the planet Venus, the complete set of general equations above could be written in the following PHP code with each of the functions representing code generated by the VSOP87 Source Code Generator tool, designed to evaluate the ordered individual sub-series summations.

$t = ($JDTT - 2451545) / 365250;

$X = Venus_X0($t) + Venus_X1($t) + Venus_X2($t)
+ Venus_X3($t) + Venus_X4($t) + Venus_X5($t);

$Y = Venus_Y0($t) + Venus_Y1($t) + Venus_Y2($t)
+ Venus_Y3($t) + Venus_Y4($t) + Venus_Y5($t);

$Z = Venus_Z0($t) + Venus_Z1($t) + Venus_Z2($t)
+ Venus_Z3($t) + Venus_Z4($t) + Venus_Z5($t);

$R = sqrt($X$X + $Y$Y + $Z*$Z);

These are the raw, instantaneous, geometric, heliocentric co-ordinates from which the apparent geocentric ecliptical and equatorial co-ordinates and distance are subsequently derived. By geometric co-ordinates we mean that no corrections for the location of the observer have yet been applied, such as for parallax, light-time, aberration, etc. This is the actual location of the planet in space, not its apparent location to the eye.

In practice, the true distance (R) at the given time needs no corrections because we are referring to its true distance, not its apparent distance at the time. Only the derived longitude and latitude co-ordinates will later need small corrections to obtain the true or local apparent positions.

Computing the heliocentric co-ordinates for both the earth and the planet at the same moment is the first and most laborious step in computing the apparent position of a planet. The rectangular XYZ co-ordinates and R are in AUs.

© Jay Tanner - 2014
FORTRAN - Breakfast of Dinosaurs
VSOP87 Theory Equations Summary Part 2

Font: http://neoprogrammics.com/vsop87/VSOP87_Equations_Summary_Part_2.html
Rectangular Coordinates (L,B,R)

VSOP87 series D is used to compute the heliocentric spherical LBR-coordinates or series C is used to compute the equivalent heliocentric rectangular XYZ-coordinates (see Part 1).

In the following VSOP87 spherical equations, we will encounter the following variables:

JDTT = Julian Day number corresponding to a given date and time (TT)
t = Julian millennia, corresponding to JDTT and reckoned from J2000.0

When we want to compute the position of a planet for a given date and time, we first compute the JDTT value and then compute the corresponding (t) value from it. This will be the actual numerical value used as the time variable in the equations.

t=JDTT − 2451545365250

The A,B,C values in each series term in the equations are taken from the original FORTRAN program data tables. There may be thousands of terms in a sub-series, each with its own set of A,B,C values. These values are used by the code generator tool to generate the numerical terms in the output source code.

A = Amplitude
B = Phase (not to be confused with the spherical B-coordinate)
C = Frequency

Indices used in the summation equations:
n = Sub-series order from 0 to 5
j = Index of term within sub-series (from 1 to k)
k = Total number of terms in sub-series (can be from 1 to multiple thousands)

Let:
L, B, R = Heliocentric Spherical Coordinates in radians and distance in AU

and
L = Heliocentric ecliptical longitude in radians
B = Heliocentric ecliptical latitude in radians (not to be confused with phase B)
R = Heliocentric radius vector (distance) in AU

These spherical coordinates are computed using the VSOP87 sub-series function modules generated by the Multi-Language VSOP87 Source Code Generator Tool.

1 AU (Astronomical Unit) = 149597870.691 km ±0.030 (NASA/JPL) = 92955807.267 mi

Speed of Light = 299792.458 km/s (NIST) = 186282.397 mi/s

Computing the Planetary Spherical Heliocentric Ecliptical LBR-Coordinates

In the following case of spherical coordinates, the heliocentric longitude and latitude (L, B) will be expressed in radians and the heliocentric distance (R) in astronomical units.

VSOP87 Series B = Spherical heliocentric ecliptical LBR-coordinates - Equinox J2000.0
VSOP87 Series D = Spherical heliocentric ecliptical LBR-coordinates - Equinox of Date

The VSOP87 B and D series correspond to the A and C series. The only difference is the type of coordinates used and the equinox to which they are referred. The method of computation is essentially the same.

These spherical coordinate equations are analogous to the equations used to compute the rectangular coordinates in part 1, with the computational roles of (X, Y, Z) being replaced by (L, B, R) respectively.

For each order (n), the VSOP87 (Ln Bn Rn) sub-series summations may be expressed as

L=∑i=05 li = l0+l1+l2+l3+l4+l5

B=∑i=05 bi = b0+b1+b2+b3+b4+b5

R=∑i=05 ri = r0+r1+r2+r3+r4+r5

There are six orders of LBR sub-series summations (n=0 to n=5). The above sub-series summations are computed separately for each order (n=0 to n=5) for each of the k terms of the given sub-series. The essential source code to compute the numerical values of these coordinates for any given moment over spans of thousands of years can be generated by the VSOP87 Source Code Generator tool.

The six separate partial summations returned by the modules for the respective sub-series are in turn summed to obtain the final, complete ecliptical spherical LBR-coordinates of the planet.

For each order (n), from 0 to 5, the VSOP87 (ln bn rn) sub-series summations
may be expressed as:

ln=⎛⎝∑j=1k AL,n,j⋅cos(BL,n,j + t⋅CL,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn

bn=⎛⎝∑j=1k AB,n,j⋅cos(BB,n,j + t⋅CB,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn

rn=⎛⎝∑j=1k AR,n,j⋅cos(BR,n,j + t⋅CR,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn

The complete VSOP87 solutions in terms of spherical variables can be expressed by
the following double summations.

L=∑n=05⎛⎝⎛⎝∑j=1k AL,n,j⋅cos(BL,n,j + t⋅CL,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn⎞⎠

B=∑n=05⎛⎝⎛⎝∑j=1k AB,n,j⋅cos(BB,n,j + t⋅CB,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn⎞⎠

R=∑n=05⎛⎝⎛⎝∑j=1k AR,n,j⋅cos(BR,n,j + t⋅CR,n,j)⎞⎠⋅tn⎞⎠

Example For The Planet Mars

As an example, for the planet Mars, the complete system of equations could be written in the following PHP code with each of the functions representing code generated by the VSOP87 Source Code Generator tool, designed to evaluate the ordered sub-series summations.

After using the tool to generate the source code for the ordered sub-functions, the programmer then only needs to write the following simple PHP code to call and sum the six returned sub-series values to obtain the respective heliocentric LBR co-ordinates.

$t = ($JDTT - 2451545) / 365250;

$L = Mars_L0($t) + Mars_L1($t) + Mars_L2($t)
+ Mars_L3($t) + Mars_L4($t) + Mars_L5($t);

$B = Mars_B0($t) + Mars_B1($t) + Mars_B2($t)
+ Mars_B3($t) + Mars_B4($t) + Mars_B5($t);

$R = Mars_R0($t) + Mars_R1($t) + Mars_R2($t)
+ Mars_R3($t) + Mars_R4($t) + Mars_R5($t);

These are the raw, instantaneous, geometric, heliocentric co-ordinates from which the apparent geocentric ecliptical and equatorial coordinates and distance are subsequently derived. By raw geometric coordinates we mean that no corrections for the location of the observer have yet been applied, such as for light-time, aberration, horizontal parallax, etc. This is the actual location of the planet in space, not its apparent location to the eye, which will require the aforementioned corrections.

The heliocentric spherical longitude (L) and latitude (B) will be returned in radians which will need to be converted to degrees. The longitude value will then need to be modulated to fall in the range from 0 to 360 degrees. The heliocentric distance or radius vector (R) will be returned in AUs.

Computing the heliocentric coordinates for both the earth and the planet at the same moment is the first and most laborious step in computing the apparent position of a planet. Once that is accomplished, it becomes trivial to convert heliocentric coordinates into geocentric or other coordinates.

© Jay Tanner - 2014
FORTRAN - Breakfast of Dinosaurs
Multi-Language VSOP87 Source Code Generator Tool

On: http://neoprogrammics.com/vsop87/source_code_generator_tool/

The purpose of this Multi-Language VSOP87 Source Code Generator Tool is to automate the process of writing of the primary programming source code needed to perform the core computations for the heliocentric coordinates of the major planets from Mercury to Neptune according to the full-precision VSOP87 theory. It is based on and adapted from the original FORTRAN program and related data files. I used this tool for accelerating the development of this web site and also for developing similar PC software.

The first step in computing the apparent position of a planet is computing the heliocentric coordinates (such as X,Y,Z) for both the planet and the Earth at the same moment. In practice, writing the full-precision, hard-coded VSOP87 source code manually would be too prohibitive a task for a single human to attempt, due to the multiple thousands of mathematical terms, and very easily prone to typographical errors. A single erroneous digit could be fatal until it was found and corrected. This program does all the hard work and writes the complete core VSOP87 source code, in a matter of seconds, for all the program functions needed to compute the geometric (prior to any corrections) heliocentric coordinates on demand for any given moment over spans of thousands of years.

The programmer simply needs to copy/paste the source code generated by the tool to his/her program development environment and build upon it. Generally, for the geocentric positions as tabulated in the standard astronomical almanacs, VSOP87 series C or D is used. Series C is used on this web site.

In most cases, ready-to-use functions code should be returned, around which one can build a long-term astronomical ephemeris or other program requiring very accurate computation of actual planetary positions in space-time at any given moment.

This programming tool can save much time and labor for those do-it-yourself astro-programmers wishing to use the full-precision VSOP87 theory in their work to create custom Internet, PC or Mac software to compute planetary positions from scratch.
NOTES:

    The time required to generate and return the source code may vary depending on the quality, speed and type of the Internet connection you have. There is the very extremely remote probability that the returned code could become randomly corrupted during transmission. This is beyond anyone's control, but very, very unlikely.

    Apparently the Opera browser (at least at v12.01.1532) has problems with this program. The generated source code gets corrupted, but only by the Opera browser for some unknown reason. The only workaround, should you encounter this problem, appears to be using another web browser, such as Internet Explorer, Firefox or Safari, if you use this source code generator program. So far, repeated experiments have shown this glitch to only occur when using the Opera browser. (1st reported by Kirill G., Russia).

© Jay Tanner - PHP Science Labs - 2015 - 3.61

See too:

ftp://cdsarc.u-strasbg.fr/pub/cats/VI%2F81/vsop87.txt

http://cdsarc.u-strasbg.fr/viz-bin/qcat?VI/81/
